<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes" ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">

]>

<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-softwire-map-dhcp-02"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="MAP DHCPv6 Options">DHCPv6 Options for Mapping of Address
    and Port</title>

    <author fullname="Tomasz Mrugalski" initials="T." surname="Mrugalski">
      <organization abbrev="ISC">Internet Systems Consortium,
      Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>950 Charter Street</street>
          <city>Redwood City</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94063</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 650 423 1345</phone>
        <email>tomasz.mrugalski@gmail.com</email>
	<uri>http://www.isc.org/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <!-- Med and Xiaohong requested to be removed from the authors list
      <author fullname="Mohamed Boucadair" initials="M." surname="Boucadair">
      <organization>France Telecom</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
	  <street></street>
          <city>Rennes</city>
          <code>35000</code>
          <country>France</country>
        </postal>
        <email>mohamed.boucadair@gmail.com</email>
	<uri>http://www.francetelecom.com/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>-->

    <author initials="X." surname="Deng" fullname="Xiaohong Deng">
      <!-- <organization></organization> -->
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>6 Cordelia St.</street>
          <code>QLD 4101</code>
          <city>South Brisbane</city>
          <country>Australia</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+61 3858 3128</phone>
        <email>dxhbupt@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Ole Troan" initials="O" surname="Troan">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Telemarksvingen 20</street>
          <city>Oslo</city>
          <code>N-0655</code>
          <country>Norway</country>
        </postal>
        <email>ot@cisco.com</email>
        <uri>http://cisco.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Wojciech Dec" initials="W" surname="Dec">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city></city>
          <region></region>
          <code></code>
          <country>The Netherlands</country>
        </postal>
        <phone></phone>
        <facsimile></facsimile>
        <email>wdec@cisco.com</email>
        <uri>http://cisco.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="C.X." surname="Bao" fullname="Congxiao Bao">
      <organization abbrev="Tsinghua University">
      CERNET Center/Tsinghua University</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Room 225, Main Building, Tsinghua University</street>
          <city>Beijing</city> <code>100084</code>
          <country>CN</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+86 10-62785983</phone>
        <email>congxiao@cernet.edu.cn</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Leaf Y. Yeh" initials="L." surname="Yeh">
      <organization abbrev="Huawei">Huawei Technologies</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city>Shenzhen</city>
          <region></region>
          <code></code>
          <country>P. R. China</country>
        </postal>
        <phone></phone>
        <facsimile></facsimile>
        <email>leaf.yeh.sdo@gmail.com</email>
        <uri></uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <!-- Qiong Sun requested joining author team as well (22.10.2011 12:10) -->

    <date />

    <area>Internet</area>
    <workgroup>Softwire WG</workgroup>
    <keyword>MAP</keyword>
    <keyword>DHCPv6</keyword>

    <!--  SECTION 0:  Abstract                      -->

    <abstract>
      <t>This document specifies DHCPv6 options for the provisioning
      of Mapping of Address and Port (MAP) Customer Edge (CE) devices,
      based on the MAP paramaters defined in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-softwire-map"></xref>.</t>

      <t></t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <!--  SECTION 1:  Introduction                  -->

    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>Mapping of Address and Port (MAP) defined in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-softwire-map"></xref> is a mechanism for providing IPv4
      connectivity service to end users over a service provider's IPv6
      network, allowing for shared or dedicated IPv4 addressing. It consists
      of a set of one or more MAP Border Relay (BR) routers, responsible for
      stateless forwarding, and one or more MAP Customer Edge (CE) routers,
      that collectively form a MAP Domain when configured with common MAP
      rule-sets. In a residential broadband deployment the CE is sometimes
      referred to as a Residential Gateway (RG) or Customer Premises Equipment
      (CPE).</t>

      <t>A typical MAP CE will serve its end-user with one WAN side interface
      connected to an operator domain providing a MAP service. To function in
      the MAP domain, the CE requires to be provisioned with the appropriate
      MAP service paramaters for that domain. Particularly in larger networks
      it is not feasible to configure such parameters manually, which forms
      the requirement for a dynamic MAP provisioning mechanism that is defined
      in this document based on the existing DHCPv6 <xref
      target="RFC3315"></xref> protocol. The configuration of the MAP BR is
      outside of scope of this document.</t>

      <t>This document specifies the DHCPv6 options that allow MAP CE
      provisioning, based on the definitions of parameters provided in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-softwire-map"></xref>, and is applicable to both MAP-E
      and MAP-T transport variants. The definition of DHCPv6 options for MAP
      CE provisioning does not preclude the definition of other dynamic
      methods for configuring MAP devices, or supplementing such
      configuration, nor is the use of DHCPv6 provisioning mandatory for MAP
      operation.</t>

      <t>Since specification of MAP architecture is still expected to
      evolve, DHCPv6 options may have to evolve too to fit the revised
      MAP specification.
      </t>

      <t>Defined proposal is not a dynamic port allocation mechanism.
      </t>

      <t>Readers interested in deployment considerations are encouraged
      to read <xref target="I-D.mdt-softwire-map-deployment" />.</t>
    </section>

    <!--  SECTION 2: REQUIREMENTS LANGUAGE                                         -->

    <section anchor="conventions" title="Conventions">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119 <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="description" title="MAP Information">
      <t>The following presents the information parameters that are used to
      configure a MAP CE:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>A Default Mapping Rule (DMR). This rule governs the default
          forwarding/mapping behaviour of the MAP CE, ie it informs the CE of
          the BR router's address or prefix that is typically used as a
          default. The DMR is a mandatory parameter for a MAP CE.</t>

          <t>A Basic Mapping Rule (BMR). This rule governs the MAP
          configuration of the CE, including that of completing the CE's MAP
          IPv6 address, as well as deriving the CEs IPv4 parameters. Key
          parameters of a BMR include: i) The IPv4 Prefix - Used to derive the
          CE's IPv4 address; ii) The Embedded Address bit length - Used to
          derive how many, if any, of the CE's IPv6 address is mapped to the
          IPv4 address. iii) The IPv6 prefix - used to determine the CE's IPv6
          MAP domain prefix that is to form the base for the CE's MAP address.
          The BMR is an optional rule for a MAP CE.</t>

          <t>A Forward Mapping Rule (FMR). This rule governs the MAP CE-CE
          forwarding behaviour for IPv4 destinations covered by the rule. The
          FMR is effectively a special type of an BMR, given that it shares
          exactly the same configuration parameters, except that these
          parameters are only applied for setting up forwarding. Its presence
          enables a given CE to communicate directly in "mesh mode" with other
          CEs. The FMR is an optional rule, and the absence of such a rule
          indicates that the CE is to simply use its default mapping rule for
          all destinations.</t>

          <t>Transport mode; encapsulation (MAP-E) or translation (MAP-T)
          modes to be used for the MAP CE Domain.</t>

          <t>Additional parameters. The MAP specification allows great
          flexibility in the level of automation a CE uses to derive its IPv4
          address and port-sharing (PSID), ranging from full derivation of
          these parameters from the CE's IPv6 prefix, to full parametrization
          of MAP configuration independent of the CE's IPv6 prefix. Optional
          parameters such as the PSID allow this flexibility.</t>
        </list></t>

      <!--
      <t>Discussion: Qiong Sun also proposed to add deployment mode
      here.  Jacni Qin recommends against it. Deployment mode is to
      notify whether CE is in Hub and spoke mode or mesh. In Hub and
      spoke mode, only the first default MAP mapping rule is needed
      in the following MAP procedure. While in mesh mode, all MAP
      mapping rules are included to achieve CE-CE traffic
      optimization. Tomek: I believe that hub and spoke or mesh
      affects number of rules, so server will provision one (hub and
      spoke) or many (mesh) rules. CE does not need to explicitly be
      information about this. It can derive this information in a
      simple manner: if (number of rules>1) then mode=mesh else
      mode=hub_and_spoke.</t> -->

      <!-- Tomek: Discussion resolved: see additional comment in "MAP
           Container Option" section. Algo for detecting mode: In th hub
           and spoke mode, all traffic should be forwarded using
           DMR. Hub and spoke mode is achieved with a BMR IPv4 rule
           prefix length of 32 and no further FMR. -->
    </section>

    <!-- conventions -->

    <!--  SECTION 3: DESCRIPTION                                                   -->

    <section title="DHCPv6 MAP Options">
      <t>The DHCPv6 protocol is used for MAP CE provisioning following regular
      DHCPv6 notions, with the MAP CE assuming a DHCPv6 client role, and the MAP
      parameters provided by the DHCPv6 server following typical DHCPv6 server
      side policies. The format and usage of the MAP options is defined in the
      following sections.</t>

      <t>Discussion: As the exact parameters required to configure MAP
      rules and MAP in general are expected to change, this section
      is expected to be updated and follow changes in the <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-softwire-map"></xref>.</t>

      <!-- <t>Discussion: Proposed layout assumes that several simple
      options are used. Such approach simplifies implementation as it
      is much easier for implementors to reuse existing code handling
      such options. This design choice comes at a cost,
      however. Clients must perform checks if provided set of options
      is complete. Alternatively, it would be possible to define one
      complex option that contains all mandatory
      parameters. </t> -->

      <t>Discussion: It should be noted that initial concept of 4rd/MAP
      provisioning was presented in DHC working group meeting. It used
      one complex option to convey all required parameters. Strong
      suggestion from DHC WG was to use several simpler
      options. Options (possibly nested) are preferred over
      conditional option formatting. See DHCP option guidelines
      document <xref target="I-D.ietf-dhc-option-guidelines"/>).</t>

      <t>Server that supports MAP configuration and is configured to
      provision requesting CE MUST include exactly one OPTION_MAP
      option in a REPLY message for each MAP domain. It is envisaged
      that in typical network, there will be only one MAP domain
      deployed.</t>

      <section anchor="what-where" title="MAP Options Cardinality">
        <t>Server configured to provision MAP configuration SHOULD return one
        MAP Container Option for each MAP domain, when requested by clients. As
        there will typically be only one MAP Domain configured, server will
        typically return a single instance of MAP Container Option.</t>

        <t>Returned MAP Container Option MUST include exactly one MAP DMR Rule
        option. It also MAY include zero or more MAP Rule Options. It also
        MAY include MAP Port Parameters option. It MAY include additional 
        options that may be defined in the future.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="option-map" title="MAP Container Option">
        <t>This MAP Container Option specifies the container used to group
        all rules and optional port parameters for a specified MAP domain.</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="img-map-option" title="MAP Container Option">
          <preamble></preamble>

          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|        OPTION_MAP             |         option-length         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     flags     |                                               .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+    encapsulated-options (variable length)     .
.                                                               .
+---------------------------------------------------------------+]]>
	</artwork>
        </figure>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>option-code: OPTION_MAP (TBD1)</t>

            <t>option-length: 1 + Length of encapsulated options</t>

            <t>flags: This 8-bits long conveys the MAP Flags that apply to
            all encapsulated options. The meaning of specific bits is explained in 
            <xref target="img-map-option-flag"/>.</t>

            <t>encapsulated-options: options associatied with this MAP domain.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>The encapsulated options field encapsulates those options that are
        specific to this MAP Option. Currently there are three options that MAY
        appear here: OPTION_MAP_RULE, OPTION_MAP_DMR and OPTION_MAP_PORTPARAMS.
        Other options suitable for a MAP domain may be defined in the future.
        A DHCP message MAY include multiple MAP Container Options (representing
        multiple MAP domains), but typically it will have only one.</t>

        <t>The Format of the MAP flags field is:</t>

<t><figure align="center" anchor="img-map-option-flag"
            title="MAP Option Flags">
            <preamble></preamble>

            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|Reserved     |T| 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+]]> 
          </artwork>
          </figure><list style="symbols">
            <t>Reserved: 7-bits reserved for future use.</t>

            <t>T: 1 bit field that specifies transport mode to use:
            translation (0) or encapsulation (1).</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Discussion: It was suggested to also provision information whether
        MAP network is working in hub and spoke or mesh mode. That is not
        necessary, as mesh mode is assumed when there is at least one FMR
        present.</t>

      </section>

      <section title="MAP Rule Option">
        <t>Figure <xref target="img-option-rule"/> shows the format of the MAP
        Rule option used for conveying the BMR and FMR.</t>

        <t>Server includes zero or more MAP Rule Options in MAP Container Option.</t>

        <t>Server MAY send more than one MAP Rule Option, if it is
        configured to do so. Clients MUST NOT send MAP Rule
        Option.</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="img-option-rule"
                title="MAP Rule Option">
          <preamble></preamble>

          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|        OPTION_MAP_RULE        |         option-length         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|  prefix4-len  |               rule-ipv4-prefix                |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| (continued)   |     ea-len    |  rule-flags  |  prefix6-len   |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                       rule-ipv6-prefix                        |
|                       (variable length)                       |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
.             encapsulated-options (variable length)            .
.                                                               .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+]]>
	</artwork>
        </figure>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>option-code: OPTION_MAP_RULE (TBD2)</t>

            <t>option-length: length of the option, excluding
            option-code and option-length fields, including length of
            all encapsulated options, expressed in bytes.</t>

            <t>prefix4-len: 8 bits long field expressing the bit mask length
            of the IPv4 prefix specified in the rule-ipv4-prefix field.</t>

            <!-- tomek todo: Do we want to restrict values to 0-32 here? -->

            <t>rule-ipv4-prefix: a fixed length 32 bit field that specifies
            the IPv4 prefix for the MAP rule. </t>

            <t>ea-len: 8 bits long field that specifies the Embedded-Address
            (EA) bit length. Values allowed range from 0 to 48.</t>

            <t>rule-flags: 8 bits long field carrying flags applicable to the
            rule. The meaning of specific bits is explained in
            <xref target="img-rule-flags"/>.</t>

            <t>prefix6-len: 8 bits long field expressing the bit mask length
            of the IPv6 prefix specified in the rule-ipv6-prefix field.</t>

            <t>rule-ipv6-prefix: a variable length field that specifies the
            IPv6 domain prefix for the MAP rule. The field is padded with
            follow up zero bits up to the nearest octet boundary when prefix6-len
            is not divisible by 8.</t>

            <t>encapsulated options: a variable field that may contain zero or
            more options that specify additional parameters for this MAP
            BMR/FMR rule. Currently there are no such options defined, but
            they may be defined in the future.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>The value of the EA-len and prefix4-len SHOULD be equal to or
        greater than 32.</t>

        <t>The Format of the MAP Rule Flags field is:<figure align="center"
            anchor="img-rule-flags" title="MAP Rule Flags">
            <preamble></preamble>

            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|Reserved     |F| 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Reserved: 7-bits reserved for future use as flags.</t>

            <t>F-Flag: 1 bit field that specifies whether the rule is to be
            used for forwarding (FMR). 0x0 = This rule is NOT used as a FMR.
            0x1 = This rule is also a FMR.</t>

            <t>Note: BMR rules can be also FMR rules by setting the F flag.
            BMR rules are determined by a match of the Rule-IPv6-prefix
            against the CPE's prefix(es).</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>It is expected that in a typical MAP deployment scenarios, there
        will be a single DMR and a single BMR, which could also be designated
        as an FMR using the F-Flag.</t>

        <t>Discussion: This option format attempts to use option formats
        recommended by <xref target="I-D.ietf-dhc-option-guidelines"/>, namely
        variable length prefix formats. It should be noted that this format
        follows prefix length + prefix notation. Reasons for using variable
        IPv6 prefix field, but fixed IPv4 prefix are given in
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-dhc-option-guidelines"/>, Section 5.9.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="MAP DMR Option">
        <t>MAP DMR Option is used to convey values for Default Mapping Rule.
        MAP DMR Option MUST appear in each MAP Container Option exactly once.
        It MUST NOT appear in the DHCP message directly. Figure <xref
        target="img-option-dmr"/> shows the format of the MAP Rule option used
        for conveying a DMR.</t>

        <t><figure align="center" anchor="img-option-dmr"
            title="MAP DMR Option">
            <preamble></preamble>

            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|        OPTION_MAP_DMR         |         option-length         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|dmr-prefix6-len|            dmr-ipv6-prefix                    |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+           (variable length)                   |
.                                                               .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
.            encapsulated-options (variable length)             .
.                                                               .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+


]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>option-code: OPTION_MAP_DMR (TBD3)</t>

            <t>option-length: 1 + length of dmr-ipv6-prefix + encapsulated
            options, specified in bytes.</t>

            <t>dmr-prefix6-len: 8 bits long field expressing the bit mask
            length of the IPv6 prefix specified in the dmr-ipv6-prefix
            field.</t>

            <t>dmr-ipv6-prefix: a variable length field that specifies the
            IPv6 prefix or address for the MAP BR. This field is padded with
            follow up zeros to the nearest octet boundary when
            dmr-prefix6-len is not divisible by 8.</t>

            <t>encapsulated options: nested options associatied to
            this MAP DMR option. Currently there are no such options
            defined, but they may be defined in the future.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="option-portparams" title="MAP Port Parameters Option">
        <t>Port Parameters Option specifies optional Rule Port Parameters that
        MAY be provided as part of the Mapping Rule. It MAY appear as
        encapsulated option in OPTION_MAP option. It MUST NOT appear directly in a
        message. It MUST NOT appear in OPTION_MAP_RULE nor OPTION_MAP_DMR
        options.</t>

        <t>See <xref target="I-D.ietf-softwire-map"/>, Section 5.1
        for detailed description of MAP algorithm that explains meaning of all 
        parameters.</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="img-option-portparams"
                title="MAP Port Parameters Option">
          <preamble></preamble>
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     OPTION_MAP_PORTPARAMS     |         option-length         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|   offset      |    PSID-len   |              PSID             |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>option-code: OPTION_MAP_PORTPARAMS (TBD4)</t>

            <t>option-length: 4</t>

            <t>offset: (PSID offset) 8 bits long field that specifies
            the numeric value for the MAP algorithm's excluded port
            range/offset bits (A-bits), as per section 5.1.1 in <xref
            target="I-D.ietf-softwire-map"></xref>. Allowed values
            are between 0 and 16, with the default value being 4.</t>

            <t>PSID-len: Bit length value of the number of significant
            bits in the PSID field. (also known as 'k'). When set to
            0, the PSID field is to be ignored. After the first 'a'
            bits, there are k bits in the port number representing
            valid of PSID. Subsequently, the address sharing ratio
            would be 2^k.</t>

            <t>PSID: Explicit 16-bit (unsigned word) PSID value. The
            PSID value algorithmically identifies a set of ports
            assigned to a CE. The first k-bits on the left of this
            2-octets field is the PSID value.  The remaining (16-k)
            bits on the right are padding zeros.</t>

          </list>
        </t>

        <t>When receiveing the Port Parameters option with an explicit
        PSID, the client MUST use this explicit PSID in configuring
        its MAP interface. </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="example" title="MAP Options Examples">
        <t>DHCPv6 server provisioning a single MAP Rule to a CE
        (DHCPv6 client) will convey the following MAP options in its
        messages:</t>

        <section title="BMR Option Example">
          <figure align="center" anchor="img-bmr-example"
                  title="BMR Option Example">
            <preamble></preamble>
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
TODO: Reflect example in section 5.2 of MAP draft
            ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>

        <section title="FMR Option Example">
          <figure align="center" anchor="img-fmr-example"
                  title="FMR Option Example">
            <preamble></preamble>
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
TODO: Reflect example in section 5.3 of MAP draft
            ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>

        <section title="DMR Option Example">
          <figure align="center" anchor="img-dmr-example"
                  title="DMR Option Examples">
            <preamble></preamble>
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
TODO: Reflect example in section 5.4 of MAP draft
            ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="DHCPv6 Server Behavior">
      <t><xref target="RFC3315">RFC 3315 Section 17.2.2</xref> describes how a
      DHCPv6 client and server negotiate configuration values using the ORO.
      As a convenience to the reader, we mention here that a server will by
      default not reply with a MAP Rule Option if the client has not
      explicitly enumerated it on its Option Request Option.</t>

      <t>A Server following this specification MUST allow the configuration of
      one or more MAP Rule Options, exactly one DMR Option and optional Port
      Parameters Option and SHOULD send such options grouped under a single MAP
      Container Option.</t>

      <t>Server MUST include a MAP Container Option (which encapsulates all MAP
      Rule, MAP DMR, and MAP Port parameters Options) in its responses if client
      requested it using OPTION_MAP in client's Option Request Option (ORO).</t>

      <t>Server MAY include more than one MAP Container Options only in the
      unlikely case of having more than one MAP Domain configured.</t>

      <!-- sadly, with introduction of OPTION_PORTPARAMS that is no longer true.
      <t>Rules assignment is a stateless process from the server's
      perspective. Server does not need to maintain a state of rules
      provisioned to clients, track lifetimes, expire outdated rules
      etc. Server SHOULDs assign the same set of rules to all CEs in
      one MAP Domain, unless there are several classes of CEs defined,
      e.g. regular and premium users. In such case, each class of CEs
      is expected to get the same set of rules. Server is not expected
      to track MAP rules on a per CE basis. Exact assignment of
      specific rules to a specific CEs is outside of scope of this
      document.</t> -->

      <t>The server MUST be capable of following per client assignment rules
      when assigning MAP options.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="DHCPv6 Client Behavior">
      <t>A MAP CE acting as DHCPv6 client will request MAP configuration to be
      assigned by the DHCPv6 server located in the ISP network. A client
      supporting MAP functionality SHOULD request OPTION_MAP option in its ORO
      in SOLICIT, REQUEST, RENEW, REBIND and INFORMATION-REQUEST messages.</t>

      <t>When processing received MAP options the following behaviour is
      expected:<list style="symbols">
          <t>A client MUST support processing multiple received
          OPTION_MAP_RULE options in a OPTION_MAP option</t>

          <t>A client receiving an unsupported MAP option, or an unrecognized
          parameter value SHOULD discard the entire OPTION_MAP.</t>

          <t>Exactly one OPTION_MAP_DMR is allowed per OPTION_MAP option. Client
          MUST ignore entire OPTION_MAP if there is zero or more than one
          MAP DMR Option.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>The client MUST be capable of applying the received MAP option
      parameters for the configuration of the local MAP instance.</t>

    <t>Note that system implementing MAP CE functionality may have
      multiple network interfaces, and these interfaces may be
      configured differently; some may be connected to networks that
      call for MAP, and some may be connected to networks that are
      using normal dual stack or other means.  The MAP CE system
      should approach this specification on an interface-by-interface
      basis.  For example, if the CE system is attached to multiple
      networks that provide the MAP Mapping Rule Option, then the CE
      system MUST configure a MAP connection (i.e. a translation or
      encapsulation) for each interface separately as each MAP
      provides IPv4 connectivity for each distinct interface. Means to
      bind a MAP configuration to a given interface in a multiple
      interfaces device are out of scope of this document.</t>
    </section>

<section title="Usage of flags and paramaters">
      <t>The defined MAP options contain a number of flags and parameters that
      are intended to provide full flexibility in the configuration of a MAP
      CE. Some usage examples are:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>A MAP CE receiving an OPTION_MAP option with the T flag set to 1
          will assume a MAP-E (encapsulation) mode of operation for the domain
          and all associated rules. Conversely, when the received option has
          the T flag set to 0, the CE will assume a MAP-T (stateless NAT46
          translation) mode of operation.</t>

          <t>The presence of a OPTION_MAP_RULE option, along with IPv4 prefix
          parameters, indicates to the MAP CE that NAPT44 mode of operation is
          expected, following the address mapping rules defined in <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-softwire-map"></xref>. Conversely, the absence of
          an OPTION_MAP_RULE option indicates that NAT44 mode is not required,
          and that the MAP CE is to plainly encapsulate (MAP-E mode) or
          statelessly translate using NAT64 (MAP-T mode) any IPv4 traffic sent
          following the DMR.</t>

          <t>The MAP domain ipv6-prefix in the BMR should correspond to a
          service prefix assigned to the CPE by the operator, with the latter
          being assigned using regular IPv6 means, e.g. DHCP PD <xref
          target="RFC3633"/> or SLAAC. This parameter allows the CPE to select
          the prefix for MAP operation.</t>

          <t>The EA_LEN parameter, along with the length of the IPv4 prefix in
          the BMR option, allows the MAP CE to determine whether address
          sharing is in effect, and what is the address sharing ratio. Eg: A
          prefix4-len of 16 bits, and EA-len of 18 combines to a 32 bit IPv4
          address with a sharing ratio of 4.</t>

          <t>The use of the F(orward) flag in the BMR allows a CE to apply a
          received BMR as an FMR, thereby enabling mesh-mode for the domain
          covered by the BMR rule.</t>

          <t>In the absence of a BMR, the presence of the mandatory DMR
          indicates to the CPE the address or prefix of a BR, and makes the
          MAP CE fully compatible with DS-Lite and stateful or stateless NAT64
          core nodes. Eg a MAP CE configured in MAP-E mode, with just a DMR
          and a BR IPv6 address equivalent to that of the AFTR, effectively
          acts as a DS-Lite B4 element. For more discussion about MAP
          deployment considerations, see 
          <xref target="I-D.mdt-softwire-map-deployment"></xref>.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Deployment considerations">
      <t>Usage of PSID Option should be avoided if possible and PSID
      embedded in the delegated prefix should be used instead. This
      allows MAP deployment to not introduce any additional state in
      DHCP server. Port Parameters Option must be assigned on a per CE basis,
      thus requiring more complicated server configuration.</t>

      <t>In a typical environment, there will be only one MAP domain,
      so server will provide only a single instance of MAP Container Option that
      acts a container for MAP Rules and other options that are
      specific to that MAP domain.</t>

      <t>In case of multiple provisioning domains, as defined in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-homenet-arch"/>, one server may be required to provide
      information about more than one MAP domain.  In such case it is envisaged
      that the server will provide two or more instances of MAP Container
      Options, each with its own set of encapsulated options that define MAP
      rules for each specific MAP domain. Details of mulitple provisioning
      domains are discussed in Section 4.1 of <xref
      target="I-D.mdt-softwire-map-deployment"/>. Such a deployment is outside
      of scope for this document.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>IANA is kindly requested to allocate the following DHCPv6 option codes: TBD1 for
      OPTION_MAP, TBD2 for OPTION_MAP_RULE, TBD3 for OPTION_MAP_DMR, and TBD4
      for OPTION_MAP_PORTPARAMS. All values should be added to the DHCPv6 option
      code space defined in Section 24.3 of <xref target="RFC3315"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Implementation of this document does not present any new security
      issues, but as with all DHCPv6-derived configuration state, it is
      completely possible that the configuration is being delivered by a third
      party (Man In The Middle). As such, there is no basis to trust that the
      access over the MAP can be trusted, and it should not therefore bypass
      any security mechanisms such as IP firewalls.</t>

      <t>Readers concerned with security of MAP provisioning over
      DHCPv6 are encouraged to read <xref target="I-D.ietf-dhc-secure-dhcpv6"/>.</t>

      <t>Section XX of <xref target="I-D.ietf-softwire-map"/> discusses
      security issues of the MAP mechanism.</t>

      <t>Section 23 of <xref target="RFC3315"/> discusses
      DHCPv6-related security issues.</t>

    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>This document was created as a product of a MAP design
      team. Following people were members of that team: Congxiao Bao,
      Mohamed Boucadair, Gang Chen, Maoke Chen, Wojciech Dec, Xiaohong
      Deng, Jouni Korhonen, Xing Li, Satoru Matsushima, Tomasz
      Mrugalski, Tetsuya Murakami, Jacni Qin, Necj Scoberne, Qiong
      Sun, Tina Tsou, Dan Wing, Leaf Yeh and Jan Zorz.</t>
      <t>Former MAP design team members are: Remi Despres.</t>

      <t>Authors would like to thank Bernie Volz for his insightful
      comments and suggestions.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <!--  SECTION 8.1:  Normative References		-->

    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-softwire-map.xml" ?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3315"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3633"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119" ?>
    </references>

    <!--  SECTION 8.2:  Informative References		-->
    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5226" ?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6335"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.mdt-softwire-map-deployment.xml" ?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-homenet-arch"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dhc-option-guidelines.xml" ?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.mrugalski-dhc-dhcpv6-4rd.xml" ?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.boucadair-dhcpv6-shared-address-option.xml" ?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dhc-secure-dhcpv6.xml" ?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.murakami-softwire-4rd.xml" ?>
  </references>

  </back>
</rfc>
