<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="no" ?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes" ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">

]>

<rfc category="info" docName="draft-mdt-softwire-map-dhcp-option-00.txt"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="MAP DHCPv6 Options">DHCPv6 Options for Mapping of Address and Port</title>

    <author fullname="Tomasz Mrugalski" initials="T." surname="Mrugalski" role="editor">
      <organization abbrev="ISC">Internet Systems Consortium, Inc.
      </organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>950 Charter Street</street>
          <city>Redwood City</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94063</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 650 423 1345</phone>
        <email>tomasz.mrugalski@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Mohamed Boucadair" initials="M." surname="Boucadair">
      <organization>France Telecom</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city>Rennes</city>
          <code>35000</code>
          <country>France</country>
        </postal>
        <email>mohamed.boucadair@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Ole Troan" initials="O" surname="Troan">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Telemarksvingen 20</street>
          <city>Oslo</city>
          <code>N-0655</code>
          <country>Norway</country>
        </postal>
        <email>ot@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2011" />

    <area>Internet</area>
    <workgroup>Softwire</workgroup>
    <keyword>MAP</keyword>
    <keyword>DHCPv6</keyword>

    <!--  SECTION 0:  Abstract                      -->

    <abstract>
      <t>Generic mechanism for mapping between an IPv4 prefix, address
      or parts of thereof, and transport layer between ports and an
      IPv6 prefix or address is specified in <xref
      target="map-design"/>. This is a companion document that
      specifies provisioning mechanism of MAP rules. It defines DHCPv6
      options which are meant to be used between Customer Edge (CE)
      devices and DHCPv6 server to obtain necessary parameters to
      configure MAP rules. Since specification of MAP
      architecture is still expected to evolve, DHCPv6 options may
      have to evolve too to fit the revised MAP specification.</t>
      <t></t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <!--  SECTION 1:  Introduction                  -->

    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>Mapping of Address and Port (MAP) defined in <xref
      target="map-design" /> is an automatic mechanism for providing
      IPv4 connectivity service to end users over a service provider's
      IPv6 network. It defines MAP Border Relay (BR) router that is
      located that the edge of a MAP domain. MAP Customer Edge (CE) is
      also defined as a device typically deployed at customers'
      location.  In a residential broadband deployment, this type of
      device is sometimes referred to as a Residential Gateway (RG) or
      Customer Premises Equipment (CPE). A MAP CE may also be referred
      to simply as a "CE" within the context of MAP.</t>

      <t>A typical MAP CE adopting MAP rules will serve a residential
      site with one WAN side interface, one or more LAN side
      interfaces. To operate properly, it requires one or more MAP
      rules and additional informations. In larger networks it is
      infeasible to configure such parameters manually. Therefore
      provisioning mechanism is required. Such mechanism is defined in
      this document. It leverages existing DHCPv6 <xref
      target="RFC3315"/> protocol to deliver necessary parameters to
      CE.</t>

      <t>This document defines several DHCPv6 options that allow
      delivery of required information to configure CE. Configuration
      of the BR is outside of scope of this document. Definitions of
      used parameters are provided in <xref target="map-design" />.</t>

      <t>Since specification of MAP architecture is still expected to
      evolve, DHCPv6 options may have to evolve too to fit the revised
      MAP specification.
      </t>
    </section>

    <!--  SECTION 2: REQUIREMENTS LANGUAGE                                         -->

    <section anchor="conventions" title="Conventions">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119 <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- conventions -->

    <!--  SECTION 3: DESCRIPTION                                                   -->

    <section anchor="description" title="Provisioning mechanism">
      <t>TODO: Describe that CE acting as a DHCPv6 client requests
      options that are being provided by a DHCPv6 server located
      somewhere in ISP network.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="DHCPv6 Options Format">
      <t>DHCPv6 protocol is used for CE provisioning. Several new
      options are defined for conveying MAP-specific parameters. Their
      format and usage is defined in the following sections.</t>

      <t>Discussion: Proposed layout assumes that several simple
      options are used. Such approach simplifies implementation as it
      is much easier for implementors to reuse existing code handling
      such options. This design choice comes at a cost,
      however. Clients must perform checks if provided set of options
      is complete. Alternatively, it would be possible to define one
      complex option that contains all mandatory
      parameters. </t>
      <t>Discussion: It should be noted that initial concept of 4rd
      provisioning was presented in DHC working group meeting. It used
      one complex option to convey all required parameters. Strong
      suggestion from DHC WG was to use several simpler
      options. Options (possibly nested) are preferred over
      conditional option formatting. See DHCP option guidelines
      document <xref target="I-D.ietf-dhc-option-guidelines"/>).</t>

      <section title="MAP Options Cardinality">
        <t>MAP CE requires one or more MAP rules. Each rule consists
        of the following parameters:</t>
        <t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>BR Prefix, consisting of 128-bit field representing IPv6
          prefix with 8-bit long prefix length</t>
          <t>Rule IPv6 Prefix, consisting of 128-bit field
          representing IPv6 prefix with 8-bit long prefix length</t>
          <t>Rule IPv4 Prefix, consisting of 32-bit long IPv4 address
          nad 8-bit long prefix length</t>
          <t>L value that designates delegated prefix length.</t>
        </list>
        </t>

        <t>The following notation is proposed for rule presentation:</t>

        <t>{BR Prefix, [Rule IPv6 Prefix, Rule IPv4 Prefix, L]}</t>

        <t>where L designates a length of a prefix delegated to CE,
        using OPTION_IA_PD, as defined in <xref
        target="RFC3633"/>.</t>

        <t>Besides requiring at least one MAP rule, CE must also be
        informed about transport mode (translation or
        encapsulation).</t>

        <t>BR Prefix does not have to be unique and MAY be shared
        between several mapping rules.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="MAP Rule Option">
        <t>OPTION_MAP_RULE. A container option than groups parameters
        for specific rule.</t>
        <t>Discussion: Do we need to distinguish or reference rules?
        (i.e. Is some kind of ID field required?)</t>
        <t>Server MAY send more than one MAP Rule Option, if it is
        configured to do so. Clients MUST NOT send MAP Rule
        Option.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="option-br-prefix" title="MAP BR Prefix">
        <t>OPTION_MAP_BR_PREFIX6. This option defines BR Prefix. It
        contains 128-bit field that specify the IPv6 prefix itself and
        8-bit prefix length field.</t>
        <t>MAP BR Prefix MUST NOT appear in places other than
        suboption of MAP Rule Option.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="option-prefix6" title="MAP Rule IPv6 Prefix">
        <t>OPTION_MAP_PREFIX6. This option defines MAP Rule IPv6
        Prefix. It contains 128-bit field that specify the IPv6 prefix
        itself and 8-bit prefix length field.</t>
        <t>MAP Rule IPv6 Prefix MUST NOT appear in places other than
        suboption of MAP Rule Option.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="option-prefix4" title="MAP Rule IPv4 Prefix">
        <t>OPTION_MAP_PREFIX4. This option defines MAP Rule IPv4
        Prefix. It contains 32-bit field that specify the IPv4 address
        itself and 8-bit prefix length field. Note that this is not a
        typical netmask used in IPv4. For length values smaller than
        32, this defines IPv4 prefix. For length equal 32, this
        defines IPv4 address. For values larger than 32, this defines
        shared IPv4 address with Port set ID.</t>

        <t>MAP Rule IPv6 Prefix MUST NOT appear in places other than
        suboption of MAP Rule Option.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="option-flags" title="MAP Flags Option">
        <t>OPTION_MAP_FLAGS. This option specifies MAP
        flags. Currently the only defined flag is T - transport
        mode. 0 designates translation and 1 designates encapsulation.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="example" title="MAP Options Example">
        <t>DHCPv6 server provisioning a single MAP Rule to a CE
        (DHCPv6 client) will convey the following MAP options in its
        messages:</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="img-example" title="MAP Options Example">
          <preamble></preamble>
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
<MAP_RULE>
    <MAP_BR_PREFIX6/>
    <MAP_RULE_PREFIX6/>
    <MAP_RULE_PREFIX4/>
</MAP_RULE>
<MAP_FLAGS>
]]></artwork>
        </figure>

      </section>

    </section>


    <section title="DHCPv6 Server Behavior">
      <t><xref target="RFC3315">RFC 3315 Section 17.2.2</xref>
      describes how a DHCPv6 client and server negotiate configuration
      values using the ORO.  As a convenience to the reader, we
      mention here that a server will not reply with a MAP Rule Option
      if the client has not explicitly enumerated it on its Option
      Request Option.</t>
      <t>Server conformant to this specification MUST allow
      configuration of one or more MAP Rule Options.</t>
      <t>Server MUST transmist all configured instances of the Mapping
      Rule Options with all sub-options, if client requested it using
      OPTION_MAP_RULE in its Option Request Option (ORO). Server MUST
      transmit MAP Flags Option if client requested OPTION_MAP_FLAGS
      in its ORO.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="DHCPv6 Client Behavior">
      <t>Although other use cases are allowed, in typical use case CE
      will act as DHCPv6 client and will request MAP configuration to
      be assigned by the DHCPv6 server located in the ISP network. A
      client that supports MAP CE functionality and conforms to this
      specfication MUST include OPTION_MAP_RULE and OPTION_MAP_FLAGS
      in its ORO.</t>

      <t>For proper operation, MAP CE client MUST also request IPv6
      address (OPTION_IA_NA, defined in <xref target="RFC3315"/>) and
      prefix delegation (OPTION_IA_PD, defined in <xref
      target="RFC3633"/>). MAP CE client SHOULD NOT initiate DHCPv4
      configuration as all parameters are delivered over DHCPv6.</t>

      <t>Client SHOULD request OPTION_MAP_RULE and OPTION_MAP_FLAGS
      options in SOLICIT, REQUEST, RENEW, REBIND and
      INFORMATION-REQUEST messages.</t>

      <t>If client receives more than one OPTION_MAP_RULE option, it
      MUST use all received instances. It MUST NOT use only the first
      one, while discarding remaining ones.</t>

      <t>Note that system implementing MAP CE functionality may have
      multiple network interfaces, and these interfaces may be
      configured differently; some may be connected to networks that
      call for MAP, and some may be connected to networks that are
      using normal dual stack or other means.  The MAP CE system
      should approach this specification on an interface-by-interface
      basis.  For example, if the CE system is attached to multiple
      networks that provide the MAP Mapping Rule Option, then the CE
      system MUST configure a MAP connection (i.e. a translation or
      encapsulation) for each interface separately as each MAP
      provides IPv4 connectivity for each distinct interface. Means to
      bind a MAP configuration to a given interface in a multiple
      interfaces device are out of scope of this document.</t>
    </section>


    <!--  SECTION 4:  IANA Considerations           -->

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This specification does not require any IANA actions.</t>
    </section>

    <!--  SECTION 6:  Acknowledgements                          -->

    <!--  SECTION 5:  Security Considerations           -->

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Implementation of this document does not present any new
      security issues, but as with all DHCPv6-derived configuration
      state, it is completely possible that the configuration is being
      delivered by a third party (Man In The Middle).  As such, there
      is no basis to trust that the access over the MAP can be
      trusted, and it should not therefore bypass any security
      mechanisms such as IP firewalls.</t>

      <t>Readers concerned with security of MAP provisioning over
      DHCPv6 are encouraged to familiarize with <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-dhc-secure-dhcpv6"/>.</t>

      <t>Section XX of <xref target="map-design"/> discusses security
      issues of the MAP mechanism.</t>

      <t>Section 23 of <xref target="RFC3315"/> discusses
      DHCPv6-related security issues.</t>

      <t>Section 6 of <xref target="I-D.murakami-softwire-4rd"/> discusses 4rd
      related security issues that are partially applicable to MAP mechanism.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>IANA is requested to allocate DHCPv6 option codes referencing
      this document, delineating OPTION_MAP_RULE, OPTION_MAP_BR_PREFIX6,
      OPTION_MAP_PREFIX6, OPTION_MAP_PREFIX4 and OPTION_MAP_FLAGS
      option names.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Contributors">
      <t>The members of the MAP design team are:
      <list>

        <t>Mohamed Boucadair</t>
        <t>Gang Chen</t>
        <t>Wojciech Dec</t>
        <t>Xiaohong Deng</t>
        <t>Jouni Korhonen</t>
        <t>Xing Li</t>
        <t>Maoke</t>
        <t>Satoru Matsushima</t>
        <t>Tomasz Mrugalski</t>
        <t>Jacni Qin</t>
        <t>Tina Tsou</t>
        <t>Ole Troan</t>
        <t>Dan Wing</t>
        <t>Leaf Yeh</t>
        <t>Jan Zorz</t>

      </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>None yet.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <!--  SECTION 8.1:  Normative References		-->

    <references title="Normative References">
      &rfc2119;
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3315"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3633"?>

      <reference anchor="map-design" target="">
        <front>
            <title>Mapping of Address and Port (MAP)</title>
            <author initials="O." surname="Troan" fullname="Ole Troan" role="editor">
                <organization>Cisco</organization>
            </author>
            <date day="24" month="10" year="2011" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="draft-ietf-softwire-mapping-address-and-port" value="00" />
    </reference>
    </references>
  <references title="Informative References">
    <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dhc-option-guidelines.xml" ?>
    <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.mrugalski-dhc-dhcpv6-4rd.xml" ?>
    <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.boucadair-dhcpv6-shared-address-option.xml" ?>
    <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dhc-secure-dhcpv6.xml" ?>
    <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.murakami-softwire-4rd.xml" ?>
  </references>

    <!--  SECTION 8.2:  Informative References		-->

  </back>
</rfc>
